VEER PAL SINGH

Google and IBM certified data scientist with 14 years of experience in analyzing large datasets and coming up with data driven solutions that positively affect business decisions, and likes to work in a team of 8 -12 team members.

Contact:

Mobile: +91 9289621414 Location: Dwarka, Delhi

Email: <u>veer.vsps@gmail.com</u> <u>LinkedIn</u> GitHub

Key Skills:

ETL process Power Query Big Data (Vaex) Basic and Inferential Statistics

Tools / NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-Learn, SciPy, MATLAB, Languages / Python, R, SQL, SparkML, Scala, html Supervised & Unsupervised Models / EDA, PCA, GBM, KNN, YGROOT, Nouval Naturals, Pagessian

KNN, XGBoost, Neural Networks, Regression, logistic, Classification, Clustering, Random Forest, Decision Tree, SVM **Deep Learning Models /** RNN, CNN, LSTM, GAN, AutoEncoder, Prophet, BERT, Transformer

DL & NLP Tools/ TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch, NLTK, Apache Spark, Hadoop Databases / My SQL, Postgres, NoSQL, SaaS, MongoDB Practical / AutoML, A/B testing, Tuning, Pipelines

Feature Engineering, Debugging

Model Deploy / Apache Spark, Pipeline, IOT,
Flask, Shell, Airflow and Kafka

Visualization / Bokeh, Dash, Plotly, Matplotlib BI Tools / Tableau, Excel, Minitab OS / Linux, Windows, Mac

Image Processing & Classification / Open CV, Pillow Cloud / Google Cloud, Amazon AWS, IBM Cloud Other / Gaussian Process, Markov Chain Monte Carlo, Mathematical and Statistical Modeling Aware / Java, C++, SAS, Azure

Education

MSc Mathematics
– University of Delhi
BSc Hon. Mathematics
– University of Delhi

Certifications:

Stanford University / Machine Learning DeepLearning.AI / Deep Learning IBM | Al Engineering Professional IBM | Machine Learning Professional IBM / Applied AI Professional IBM / Data Science Professional Google / Data Analytics Professional IBM / Advanced Data Science DeepLearning.AI / TensorFlow Developer Google / IT Automation with Python DeepLearning.AI / Natural Language Processing (NLP) University of Michigan / Applied Data Science with Python University of Michigan / Statistics with Python Imperial College of London/ Mathematics for Machine Learning Hong Kong Uni/ Python and Statistics for Financial Analysis EDHEC B Sch/ Investment Management with Python and ML New York University/ Machine Learning for Trading Tableau 10 Six Sigma Black Belt

Strengths:

Quick Learner Commercially Aware Collaborative

Master in Digital Marketing

Experience:

Research Data Scientist - Machine Learning & Deep Learning

Independent Consultant, Gurgaon, March, 2020-Present

- ♦ Formulated Business Intelligence processes in collaboration with clients and generated annual profit of \$2.25+ million
- Build Tableau dashboard to visualize core business like monthly recurring revenue that saves10 hours per week of manual reporting time.
- Performed data wrangling, ETL and data analysis to create visual reports, which in turn successfully drove business strategies and positively impacted sales by 24%
- Mentored and redesign the website with findings from customers and competitive research increasing website leads by 225%
- Customer retention by reducing the Churn and potential revenue saving \$ 114434
- Evolve recommender system for sending job alerts to candidates, with 9% conversion rate
- Build web traffic time series predictions by ARIMA and LSTM with MSE 0.0066
- Trained CNN with tape gradient, able to classify images 10 times faster
- ♦ Semantic image segmentation, predicts a label for every single pixel with accuracy 92.67%
- Managed a project to develop Neural Network face recognizer that encoding name and distance for the image from <= 0.7m using database.
- Teach Statistics and Research Methodology to 300+ data analysts and other professionals.

Data Science Consultant (Profit Sharing Partner)

Modex International Securities, Gurgaon, March, 2019-Feb, 2020

- Developed Trading Dashboard in Python with Bokeh to evaluate portfolio table 18% better which increased revenue by 32%.
- Created simple RNN models for stock trading that outperformed by LSTM and GRU model to achieve 17% higher accuracy.
- Implemented algo trading model using CNN and LSTM-RL agent and achieved 71% increase in fund value in one year.

Quantitative Data Analytics Specialist

ICFM India, Delhi, October, 2018-March, 2019

- Predicted option and future price 27% better by designing and developing new time series and forecasting model using Facebook Prophet.
- Developed algorithm based pair trading with a Kalman filtering approach, created a 36% reduction in monthly drift, corresponding to \$25K monthly P&L improvement.

Six Sigma Black Belt Management Consultant

Director, VSPS Pvt Ltd, Sushant Lok, Gurgaon, May, 2008 – October, 2018

- Managed projects from ITC, Reckitt Benckiser, Glaxo Smith Kline, Apollo, Aster Tele Services, Kamdhenu etc. and grow office revenue by 67% annually.
- Performed Root Cause Analysis to improve efficiency, enhanced customer service, and supported sales teams in generating \$525K in add-on revenue for existing projects.
- Reduced production losses and yield losses by 12% and increased productivity by applying focused Kaizens.
- Conduct in-depth analyses including data collection, analyses, and synthesis to optimize onboard time for new hires by 31%.

Statistics & Mathematics Tutor

Freelancer Tutor / Mathematics / Statistics / Quantitative Techniques July, 1996 – April, 2008

Mentored 2750+ graduate and post graduate students in Mathematics, Statistics and Quantitative Techniques to graduate and post graduate students with over 97% satisfaction.

<u>Projects:</u>

- ♦ Sentiment Analysis of 14 common Women's Clothing Review
- Winning Space Race Project with 94.4% test data accuracy
- ♦ Working with Real World datasets using SQL, Python & IBM DB2 on Cloud
- ♦ Employee Churn Analysis with F1 score 93.1%
- Detailed performance analysis of Stock with 10.2% annual return and VAR 9%
- Sentiment Classification using BERT with PyTorch and Hugging Face transformer with MCC 0.17